Guide to the George Edward Woodberry Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
George Edward Woodberry Papers,
1866-1951
Woodberry, George Edward, 1855-1930.
ca. 6,200 items.
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4079497
Biographical Note
Poet, critic, educator. Woodberry was chairman of Columbia University Dept. of Comparative Literature until 1904.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, documents, photographs, and printed materials of and relating to Woodberry. Included are letters from Woodberry to Melville H. Cane, John Erskine, John S. Harrison, Robert Underwood Johnson, and Joel E. Spingarn. There are 330 letters from Woodberry to Harry Harkness Flagler telling of Woodberry's daily life in Beverly, Mass. and of his travels in Europe and Africa. Additional correspondence, notes, and printed materials relate to Woodberry's life, writings, teaching career, retirement, the controversy in 1902 that led to his resignation from the Columbia University faculty in 1904, the bequest of his books to Harvard University and Phillips Exeter Academy, the Poetry Room dedicated in his honor at Harvard University, an exhibit of Woodberriana at the New York Public Library and the Woodberry Society. There are more than fifty manuscripts of his essays and poems. Among the printed materials are his poems, essays, and book reviews, most of which have been cut from The Atlantic Monthly. Other printed materials are about Woodberry, reviews of his books, obituaries, memorials, and books, many inscribed.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 6 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Aarranged Correspondence
Series III: Cataloged Manuscripts and Documents
Series IV: Printed Material
Series V: Books
Series VI: Joseph Doyle Research Materials
Subjects
Woodberry Society.; Harvard University.; Columbia University--Faculty.; Phillips Exeter Academy.; New York Public Library.; Cane, Melville, 1879-1980.; Erskine, John, 1879-1951.; Harrison, John Smith, 1877-; Johnson, Robert Underwood, 1853-1937.; Spingarn, Joel Elias, 1875-1939.; Flagler, Harry Harkness, b. 1870.; Europe--Description and travel.; Africa--Description and travel.; Beverly (Mass.)--Social life and customs.; Decedents' estates.; American literature--19th century.; American literature--20th century.; Poems.; Photoprints.; Poets, American.; College teachers.; Educators.; Critics.
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: 12-47. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
1968 M-68 Mary Flagler Cary Charitable Trust Gift
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - Correspondence of George E. Woodberry, [n.d.] & 1874-1884 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of George E. Woodberry, 1885 - 1899 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence of George E. Woodberry, 1900-1903 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence of George E. Woodberry, 1904 - 1907 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence of George E. Woodberry, 1908 - 1911 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence of George E. Woodberry, 1912 - April 1914 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence of George E. Woodberry, May 1914 - 1915 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence of George E. Woodberry, 1916 - April 1918 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence of George E. Woodberry, May 1918 - 1919 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence of George E. Woodberry, 1920 & 1921 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence of George E. Woodberry, 1922 & 1923 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence of George E. Woodberry, 1924 - 1926 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence of George E. Woodberry & typescripts, 1927 - 1929 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence to George E. Woodberry (Box 16)
  - Correspondence about George E. Woodberry (Box 17 & 18)
- Series II: Aarranged Correspondence
  - Correspondence of George E. Woodberry, 1874 - 1899, (Typescripts & copies) (Box 13A)
  - Correspondence of George E. Woodberry, 1900 -1915, (Typescripts) (Box 14)
  - Correspondence of George E. Woodberry, 1916 - 1929, (Typescripts) (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence & notes (Box 19)
- Series III: Cataloged Manuscripts and Documents
  - Manuscripts & documents (Box 20 & 21)
- Series IV: Printed Material
  - Poems (Box 22 -24)
  - Prose (Box 25 & 26)
  - Book reviews (Box 27 & 28)
  - Obituaries & memorials (Box 29)
  - Miscellaneous printed material (Box 30 & 31)
  - Photographs & miscellaneous books (Box 32)
- Series V: Books
  - Books inscribed to H.H. Flagler (Box 33)
  - Books inscribed by George E. Woodberry to Melville H. Cane (Box 34)
  - Books by George E. Woodberry signed by Melville H. Cane (Box 35 - 37)
  - Books with contributions by George E. Woodberry signed by Melville H. Cane (Box 38 & 39)
  - Books with Melville H. Cane's notes (Box 40)
  - Miscellaneous books (Box 41)
- Series VI: Joseph Doyle Research Materials
  - Miscellaneous correspondence A-K (Box 42)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence L-Y (Box 43)
  - Notes [1] (Box 44)
  - Notes [2] & printed materials (Box 45)
  - Card Files A-Z (Box 46)
  - Microfilms of material in other libraries (Box 47)